let's go somewhere fun
[Music]
today all right let's try something new
hey what's up guys My Name Is AO welcome
back to my C++ Series so today header
files and we're actually we're actually
out started off as a great day then it
started raining but I decided to get out
of town because
so we're here somewhere in
Australia and we're going to be talking
about C++ I hope you guys don't start to
think that header files are so boring
that I felt the need to just get out of
town to cover them that's just what I
just felt like doing all right so header
files what are they why do we need them
why do they even exist in C++ a lot of
other languages that you might have been
used to like Java or C they don't
actually have header files or any kind
of concept of of of two different file
types where we have our compilation file
that we actually compile like I said
Plus+ file a translation unit and then
we also have a header file which is just
this weird kind of file that we always
include in places and why is it even
there header files are actually much
more useful and they're used for much
more than just to kind of declare
certain declarations that you want to
use in multiple CPP files and as this
series kind of goes on we're just going
to learn so many new Concepts that
really do require header files in order
to work so don't dismiss them too
quickly as far as the basics of C++ goes
header files are traditionally used to
declare certain types types or functions
so that they can be used throughout your
program if you think back to my C++
compiler and Link videos I talked about
how we need certain declarations to
actually exist so that we know what
functions and types we have available to
us for example if we create a function
in one file and we want to use it in
another file C++ isn't going to know
that that function even exists when we
try and compile that other file so we
need a common place to kind of store
just declarations not definitions
because remember we can only Define a
function once we need a common place is
to store declarations for functions just
declarations no actual definitions no
body for the functions but just a place
that says hey this function exists let's
take a simple example here so suppose
that I have a function here called log
that is supposed to log something to the
console it's going to take in a conchar
message and it's going to Simply see out
that
message if I then go ahead and create an
additional file we're going to call this
log. CPP and then maybe that additional
file has something that initializes our
log and decides to log something to the
console we're going to get an error
because this log function doesn't
actually exist in this file this file
doesn't know about the log function of
course back in main here it is the log
function exists fine and we can actually
replace our hello world logging to use
that log
function and if I try and compile my
program by hitting contrl F7 you'll see
that it works fine and we don't get any
errors however back in log if I try and
compile this we get an error because of
course as far as this file is concerned
log doesn't exist so what does log. CPP
actually need in order to not error us
how do we tell it that that log function
does actually exist but it's just
defined elsewhere that is where a
function declaration comes in if we go
back to our code here I need to Simply
declare that log does exist if we go
back to main and we take a look at this
actual signature you'll see that log is
a function that returns void and takes
in one parameter which is a con CH
pointer and some child is chasing the
kangaroos that's funny so this is the
function signature we can literally just
copy this go back to log. CPP paste this
in and just close it with a semicolon
the fact that this function doesn't
actually have a body means that it is
the Declaration of the function we
haven't defined what the function
actually is what the function actually
does we've just said hey there's a
function called log that returns void
and takes in a conar pointer we've that
that function exists you can see that
our intellisense error has gone away and
if I hit contrl F7 we do compile and if
I right click on hello world and click
build to actually build my program you
can see that it links fine as well
because it's F it's found that log
function all right fantastic so great we
found a way to actually tell our log.
CPP that that that log function exists
somewhere but what if we make another
file what if I what if I make some other
file that needs to use this log function
does that mean that I also have to copy
and paste this void log declaration
everywhere I go the answer is yes you
actually do need to do that however
there is a way to make that easier
header files right what are header files
what are head files traditionally I
should say because really this is C++
you can you can do anything with
anything but header files are usually
files that get included into CPP files
so basically what we do is we copy and
paste the content of header files into
CPP files and we do that via the hash
include pre-processor directive so hash
include has the ability to copy and
paste files into other files and that is
exactly what it seems that we need to do
here we need to copy and paste this log
declaration into every file that needs
to use that log function so let's have a
go at making a header file I'm going to
write click on header files now note
these folders here are called filters
they're not actual real folders I can
create a header file under source files
there's going to be a few videos on how
Visual Studio works in the future but
for now just know that these are kind of
fake folders it doesn't matter which one
you right click on to create your header
file I'm going to create it under header
files because that makes sense but it
doesn't really matter I'm going to make
a header file called log. you'll notice
that it straight away inserted some code
for me automatically that says hash
pragma once we'll talk about that in
just a second so here I'm going to put
in my declaration I'm going to cut my
declaration from the log. cpv file and
put it into here into my header file so
now the idea is this this header file
log. I can include everywhere where I
want to be able to use log and of course
it's going to do for me what I didn't
want to do manually and that is copy and
paste this everywhere throughout every
file that requires it I don't want to
have to do that copying and pasting
myself so I've basically found a way to
kind of make it look a bit tidy and
automate it to some extent so back in
log. CPP you can see we get an error now
because we're not actually declaring
that function however if I type in hash
include
log. check that out we don't get an
error and our file compiles fantastic
what we can also do is actually included
into main.cpp now main.cpp contains the
actual definition for the function so it
doesn't really require it we can call
log anyway but just so you know it's not
going to hurt for us to actually include
log Doh into here and compile that's not
going to be a problem all right so back
in log. CPP you can see we've defined
this fantastic function called nit log
however no one actually knows about it
except for log to CPP if I want to be
able to call it from Main I'm going to
need that declaration if I call init log
over here it's going to give me an error
because that's not declared anywhere so
let's go ahead and add that function
signature in it log into our log header
file just like that fantastic make sure
that it matches the function signature
that you've actually declared in your in
your CB file so now everything seems
well in the world I'm also going to go
ahead and cut and paste this log
definition into my log file because that
makes a lot more sense now I get an
error here telling me see out is not
found that's okay I can just include IO
awesome so back in main if I run my
program we can see that we managed to
initialize our log and then log hello
world to the console fantastic all right
brilliant so let's go back to that
header file and take a look at what that
pragma one statement actually was so
here we have a statement that Visual
Studio has seemingly inserted for us
called hash pragma once what is this so
firstly anything that begins with a hash
is known as a pre-processor command or a
pre-processor directive it means that
this is going to be evaluated by the C++
pre-processor before this file actually
gets compiled pragma is essentially an
instruction that is sent to the compiler
or to the pre-processor and what pragma
once essentially means is that only
include this file once so pragma once is
something called a header guard what it
does is it prevents us from including a
single header file multiple times into a
single translation unit now I chose my
words there very carefully because you
have to understand that it does not
prevent us from including our header
file into multiple places in our program
just into a single translation unit so
a single CPP file the reason is that if
we accidentally include a file multiple
times into a single translation unit we
can get duplicate errors because we'll
be copying and pasting that entire
header file multiple times one of the
best ways to demonstrate this is if we
were to create a struct for example if I
create a struct here called player I can
leave it empty it doesn't really matter
if I were to include this file twice
into a single translation unit with no
heer Gods it would actually include that
file twice which means that I would have
two structures with exactly the same
name player we can take a look at this
example by commenting out our pragma
once and then back in log I will include
log. H twice if I try and compile my
file you can see that we get a player
struct redefinition error because we're
redefining that struct player we can
only Define one struct called player
structs need unique names so again you
say chero why would I do this I'm not a
stupid programmer I'm not as dumb as you
think why would I include a file twice
well young one this comes back to how
include Works remember how include works
is it copies and pastes files into to
other files meaning you can create a bit
of a chain of includes so you could have
a header file called player which
includes log then players included in
some other file and then maybe that
third file contains every include so if
I create another header file here called
common common is just going to contain
some common includes for example it will
include log if I go to log. and make
sure that pragma once is commented out
and into log. cppp I include log. H and
common. H if I compile my file guess
what I still get that error because that
struct player is being redefined if we
were to resolve what the pre-processor
actually did you could see that it
actually has included log twice however
back in log. if we get rid of that
comment and try and compile our file we
don't get an error because it recognizes
that log is already been included and it
does not include it twice now there is
one other way that we could add a header
guard and I actually kind of like this
four teaching purposes because it makes
a little bit more sense than some kind
of pragma once although pragma once does
look a lot cleaner the traditional way
to add header guards is via an if def so
what we can do is we can actually type
in an if and Def and then we can get it
to check some kind of symbol for example
log H we're going to Define log H and
then at the very end of our file we're
going to type in and if so what this is
going to do is first of all check to see
if a symbol called log H is actually
defined if it's not defined it's going
to go ahead and include the following
code in compilation if this was defined
then none of this will be included it'll
be all disabled so once we do pass this
initial check we're going to Define log
H which basically means that next time
we go through this code it will be
defined so it will not be repeated a
really easy way to demonstrate this is
just to copy and paste this entire
file into our log CPP
file and then if we take a look at
this I'll also comment out log.
H and common. H so you can see over here
that the first time this is all fine it
includes the file and everything's okay
and then the second time it's all gray
out because log H has already been
defined so this kind of head of guard is
something that was used a lot in the
past however now we have this new
pre-processor statement called pragma
once and so we mostly use that it
doesn't matter which one you use to some
extent although pragma once is a lot
cleaner so it's something that I
personally use and it's something that
most people do use in the industry
pretty much every compiler now supports
pragma one so there isn't it's not like
a visual studio only thing GCC clang
msvc they all support once so don't be
afraid to use it that being said if you
do find Legacy code or just code the
people have written using different
styles you may encounter this if and Def
header guard so just be wary of what it
is but again I would never write if and
F I would always use pragma ones the
last thing I want to show you is with
header guards we have this kind of
discrepancy between include statements
some include statements use quotes some
include statements use angular brackets
what is the deal deal is actually pretty
simple they mean two different things
when we compile our program we have the
ability to tell the compiler of certain
include paths these are basically paths
to folders in our computer that contain
include files if the include file that
we want to include is inside one of
these folders we can use angular
brackets to tell the compiler to search
our include path folders whereas quotes
on the other hand are usually used to
include files that are relative to the
current file so for example if I had a
file called log. that was up One
Directory from this current log. CPP
file I could use do flash to go back and
that would actually go back to a
directory because this is relative to
this current file whereas with angular
brackets they are never relative to this
current file they just have to be in one
of the include directories we'll talk
more about setting up include
directories and all that in the future I
don't want to complicate things too much
but that's basically the gist of how
this works now quotes can also be used
to specify files that are relative to
include directories that are pass to our
compiler so you can actually use quotes
anywhere I can replace this IO stream to
be in quotes and it would totally work
so angular brackets only for compiler
include paths quotes for everything
however I usually like to use them just
for relative Parts since you might as
well use the angular brackets for
something all right final thing for
today one other thing that you might
notice is this IO stream doesn't
actually look like a file because it
doesn't contain any extension it's just
called iostream what's up with that well
it actually is a file it's just that it
doesn't have an extension this is
something that whoever wrote the C++
standard Library decided to do to
basically separate out C standard
Library header files and C++ standard
Library header files header files that
are in the C standard Library will often
have a h extension on the end however
C++ files do not so this is just one
other way you can differentiate between
what is in the C standard library and
the C++ standard Library whether or not
it has that Doh extension IO stream is a
file just like anything else in fact in
visual studio if we right click on it
and hit open documents you can see that
it takes us to this IO stream header
file and if we right click on it on this
tab here and hit open containing folder
you'll see where it's actually located
on our computer inside this directory
and here it is that IO stream header
file all right so that's it header files
pretty easy we're going to be using this
extensively in this series so there'll
be plenty of examples to follow you'll
see how I use them you'll see how you
should be using them but you should Now
understand how they work and what
they're used for so anyway I'm going to
get out of here cuz it's getting really
really cold but I hope you guys enjoyed
this video let me know what you think of
this whole like me going out and doing
stuff in in I mean this is way more fun
I love traveling so this is way more fun
for me to do than just sitting at home
especially on a Saturday afternoon even
though the weather today was pretty bad
so I probably should have just sat home
but anyway I'm here now let me know what
you think of this you can follow me on
Twitter and Instagram I'm going to be
posting some of the photos I took today
on Instagram so be sure to follow me
there if you really enjoy this series
and you want to see more of these videos
you can support me on patreon.com Theo
and I will see you guys in the next
video
[Music]
goodbye
he